A Guide for the Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society, Office Files of Lisa Jordan FA589
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society, Office Files of Lisa Jordan
1998-2009
Rockefeller Archive Center
Jordan, Lisa (1964)
Ford Foundation
FA589
2.37 Cubic Feet 6 document boxes: 5 letter size and 1 legal size box
Arrangement
Collection consists of two series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 1998-2009
Series 2. Trip and convening files, 2000-2006
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the files Lisa Jordan created when she served as a Program Officer and then Deputy Director of the Ford Foundation's Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society unit (GCS). It consists of two series. The first series holds subject files which document Jordan's support of grantees focused on global civil society issues, and the second holds trips and convening files which document Jordan's organization and participation in meetings in relation to her grant portfolio and the Foundation's program strategy.
Grantees whom Lisa Jordan's work supported focused on areas such as accountability and transparency for NGOs, development banks, and other international organizations, strengthening global civil society, and the environment. Common material formats found throughout the collection include correspondence, drafts, reports, notes, proposals, and meeting materials. There is also a digital media item.
Documents in the collection indicate that Lisa Jordan's assistant Monica Brown contributed significantly to the creation and organization of the files.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
This material was originally transferred to the RAC as part of Accession 2012:049 and processed as the Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society (GCS), Office Files of Lisa Jordan collection. A later accession of material was transferred in 2021 as Accession 2021:017 and processed into the collection.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Ford Foundation; Development banks; Financial institutions, International; Globalization; Non-governmental organizations
- Subject files, 1998-2009; 1; 1.52 Cubic Feet 4 letter document boxes and a small part of 1 legal box
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains the subject files Lisa Jordan created during her time working in the Ford Foundation's Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society unit (GCS). Jordan's subject files document her management of a grant portfolio pertaining to global civil society through her positions as Program Officer and Deputy Director of GCS.
  Files in the series document grantees' work related to development bank and international financial institution reform, NGOs, and globalization.
  Common material formats found throughout the series include correspondence, drafts, reports, notes, and meeting materials. There is also one digital media item.
  - African Forum and Network on Debt and Development (AFRODAD), 2003-2007 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bank Information Center (BIC) - Transparency Campaign, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bank Information Center (BIC)'s Afghanistan Project, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bank Information Center (BIC), 2003-2006 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bank Information Center (BIC), 2004 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Opening the International Institutions: The Complete Transparency Resource and Database, 2004 April (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - Bank Information Center (BIC) Strategic Planning Workshop, Millwood, Virginia, 2006-2008 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bank Information Center (BIC) documents, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Bridge Initiative on Globalization, 2002-2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bridge Initiative International, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - CIVICUS: World Alliance for Citizen Participation, 1998-2007 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - CIVICUS: World Alliance for Citizen Participation, 2004-2008 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - doCip, 1998-2007 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - EarthRights International (ERI), 2003-2007 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Government Accountability Project (GAP), 2002-2009 (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
  - Grassroots Organizations Operating Together in Sisterhood (GROOTS), 2005-2006 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Humanitarian Accountability Project (HAP), 2002-2008 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Institute for Agriculture and Trade Policy (IATP), 2007-2008 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Institute for Agriculture and Trade Policy (IATP), 2002-2008 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Institute for Agriculture and Trade Policy (IATP), 2004-2007 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Institute for Research and Debate on Governance (IRG), 2007-2008 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - InterAction: The American Council for Voluntary International Action, 2004-2006 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - International NGO Forum on Indonesian Development (INFID), 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - International Rivers Network (IRN), 2000-2005 (Box 4, Folder 26-27)
  - London School of Economics and Political Science, 1999-2004 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - openDemocracy, 2002-2008 (Box 4, Folder 29-30)
  - Shack/Slum Dwellers International (SDI), 2000-2005 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Syracuse University - Milton Mueller, 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Transparency International (TI), 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 33)
- Trip and convening files, 2000-2006; 2; 0.85 Cubic Feet 1 legal and 1 letter document box
  Series contains the trip and convening files Lisa Jordan created during her time as a Program Officer and then Deputy Director of the Ford Foundation's Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society unit (GCS). Jordan organized and/or participated in the various meetings documented within the series. These meetings pertained to the interests of Jordan's global civil society grant portfolio as well as the program strategy of the Ford Foundation. Some meetings were hosted at the Foundation while others were held at different locations both within the United States and other countries.
  Itineraries in the series show Jordan's travels throughout the U.S., Latin America, Africa, and Europe. There are also materials like correspondence, agendas, reports, drafts, and notes in the series. Aspects of Jordan's grant portfolio focus that are highlighted by these records include the strengthening of global civil society, globalization, and accountability for NGOs.
  - Uruguay/Brazil - Changing Windows Into Doors Workshop, Montevideo, Uruguay, 2005-2006 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Chicago, Illinois, 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ) Ford Foundation Trustees Meeting, 2005-2006 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - South Africa, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Boston, Massachusetts - Laboratory for New Thinking on Foreign Policy, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ) Governance and Civil Society unit (GCS) Program Officer Orientation, 2005-2006 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Kampala, Uganda, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - 2005 trips, 2004-2006 (Box 5, Folder 41-42)
  - Italy - Practical Steps to Strengthen Global Civil Society Conference, Bellagio Centre, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Paris, France - Bridge Initiative Annual Meeting, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - 2004 trips (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - 2004 trips - Europe (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - 2004 trips - Hivos NGO Rights and Responsibilities Workshop, The Hague, Netherlands, 2003-2004 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - 2004 trips, 2003-2004 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - 2002-2003 trips (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Brazil - World Social Forum (WSF), 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Ford Foundation Joint Worldwide Meeting, San Francisco, California, 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Funder Convening on the World Social Forum (WSF), 2002 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Concept Review Workshop on New Ford Foundation Work on Globalization, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - 2000-2001 trips (Box 6, Folder 54)